Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ס"ד, Samech Daled,
sixty-four. We pick up on the second line from the top on
ס"ד Samech Daled עמוד א'. amud Aleph. We are looking at the
משנה Mishnah that was speaking about how you bring the bird sacrifices
and specifically was focusing on the southwest corner of the מזבח. Mizbeach.
And it said that three things would be done at the top
and three below.
The three that were below would be the חטאת העוף, Chatas HaOf,
the bird חטאת. Chatas. The bird חטאת, Chatas, the birds are the
reverse of the mammals. The חטאת Chatas is at the bottom, the
bird חטאת העוף, Chatas HaOf, the מנחה, Mincha, and the spilling of
the remnant of the remainder of the blood. Okay, so let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. שלושה דברים, Shlosha Devarim, חטאת העוף
דאמרן. Chatas HaOf Had Amran. How do you know that the חטאת
העוף Chatas HaOf would be done at the southwest corner? We said
it in yesterday's דף. daf. We learn it out from the מנחה
Mincha because the פסוק Pasuk connects the מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei to
the חטאת העוף Chatas HaOf and the מנחה, Mincha, it says that
you touch it to the face of the מזבח Mizbeach and you
touch it
into לפני ה'. Lipnei Hashem. So the face of the מזבח Mizbeach
is the south where you go up to the מזבח Mizbeach on
the ramp, and לפני ה' Lipnei Hashem is the west where it
is
facing the אולם Ulam and the היכל. Heichal. So that is the
southwest corner. So that's how you know the מנחה, Mincha, והגישה Vehigisha
where you do the touching of the מנחה Mincha to
that
corner, not the actual קמיצה Kmitza which could be done anywhere, but
the touching of it to the מזבח. Mizbeach. דכתיב Dechtiv והגישה אל
המזבח. Vehigisha el HaMizbeach. And again, we learn out from the face
and from לפני ה' Lipnei Hashem that it's the southwest, and from
there we get to the חטאת העוף. Chatas HaOf. And שירי הדם,
Shiurei HaDam, the remnant of the blood, when you do the of
the חטאות, Chatas HaOte, so also would be there. How do you
know that? דכתיב Dechtiv ואת כל דם הפר ישפוך אל יסוד מזבח
המזבח. Ve'et kol dam hapar yishpoch el yesod mizbach hamizbeach. Right,
all the remnant of the blood you spill at the base of
the altar. So that is when we are talking the גמרא Gemara
links the the blood of a חטאת Chatas from the that's done
at the top of the מזבח Mizbeach to what is done inside
the היכל Heichal for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And for יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, you pour it out as soon as you exit it
at the base that is facing the אולם Ulam and the היכל.
Heichal. So you pour it out at the western base. So similarly,
the גמרא Gemara learns out from when you do from the חטאת,
Chatas, when you come down from the מזבח, Mizbeach, you pour the
remnant of the blood at the base that is immediately facing where
you come down, which would be the southern side of the מזבח.
Mizbeach. Okay, so that is how you learn that all of those
things are done at that corner. Why specifically that corner? Why not
the whole southern side? And the answer is because the whole southern
side didn't have a יסוד. Yesod. There was no יסוד, Yesod, if
you'll remember we talked, on the southern side and on the east
side. Only it began at the corner, at the southwest corner, then
it went the whole west, it went the whole north, and then
it had the whole northeast corner. But the remainder of the east
and of the south had no יסוד. Yesod. Okay, so that's how
you know those three things were done at that corner. מלמעלה, Milma'ala,
so now we go back to the משנה. Mishnah. Three things were
done at that corner, the southwest corner at the
top: ניסוך המים והיין, Nisuch HaMayim VeHaYayin, the pouring of the wine
and of the oil, excuse me, of the wine and of the
water. And that was specifically at that corner because, as you'll remember,
we said that they extended the
מזבח Mizbeach to the south and to the west so that that
corner would be over where the שיתין Shittin were, where the underground
caverns were, that the pouring should be go into the מזבח Mizbeach
and be absorbed underground. Okay, so that's why that had to be
in the southwest corner. And also ועולת העוף שהיא רבה במזרח. VeOlah
HaOf she'hi raba bamizrach. And when there the bird עולת העוף, Olah
HaOf, which is at the top of the מזבח, Mizbeach, but if
there were too many of them taking place
in the southeast corner, then they would move it over to the
southwest corner. So that we have to explain. How do we know
a standard עולת העוף Olah HaOf would be in the southeast corner
at the top and then if there are too many you move
it over to the southwest? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא, Mai Tama, what's the reason
that we normally start with the southeast? רבי יוחנן אומר מפני שקרובה
מבית הדשן. Rabbi Yochanan Omer mipnei shekerova mibeis hadeshen.
That it is the one that is closest to the בית הדשן.
Beis HaDeshen. The בית הדשן Beis HaDeshen is
where the ashes are taken when you do the תרומת הדשן Trumas
HaDeshen every day from the מזבח. Mizbeach. It says you shall put
it at the side of the altar. It says the פסוק Pasuk
says ושמו אצל המזבח. Vesamo etzel hamizbeach. And when and then when
it speaks about the עולת העוף, Olah HaOf, it says that you
that you cast the the crop and the gizzard, the innards, it
says you shall you shall cast it והשליך אותו אצל המזבח. vehishlich
oto etzel hamizbeach. קדמה kedma to the east, מקום הדשן makom hadashen
where the ashes are. So we from the first פסוק pasuk by
the ashes we learned that it is you know near the מזבח,
mizbeach, you could, so that’s when or as soon as you’re coming
down it might have been to the east or to the west
of the ramp, but here from the parts from the innards of
the עולת העוף olas haof we learned that it is you know
that it is קדמה kedma to the east. So you combine those
and we learned that the place where the ashes are put are
to the east of the ramp, so they’re on the east side
of the ramp, so that gets it pretty close to the you
know to the southeast corner,
and and therefore that’s where you’re going to be casting the innards
and the entrails of the עולת העוף, olas haof, that’s where you
want to also be doing the עוף of so that it’s a
you know if you’re up there at the southeast corner then you
just throw the entrails down and you get them to the east
side of the ramp. Okay, so that’s how you would normally why
we know you would normally do the the עולת העוף olas haof
at the southeast corner. Okay, so
מיצה קרוב לבית הדשן, mitza karov lebeis hadashen, מבית הדשן mibeis hadashen
or לבית הדשן. lebeis hadashen. Okay, so that would be the best
place to do it so that you can throw them into where
the ashes were placed at the east side at the east side
of the ramp. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar rabbi yochanan: בוא וראה כמה
גדול כוחן של כהנים. bo re’e kama gadol kochan shel kohanim. Come
see how strong the כהנים kohanim were, literally the physical strength. שאין
לך קל בעופות יותר ממוראה ונוצה. she’ein lecha kal ba’ofos yoseir mimora
venotza. The
you have nothing lighter from the birds than like the crop and
like the feather, the feather that’s like on the skin around the
crop, you cut that out and you throw and you throw it
out, you know, you throw it at this place of the ashes.
And when you try to throw something light, you know, it’s very
very hard to throw something light a long distance, you want something
to be dense if you want to throw it a long distance.
So you have this thing that is very light, and nevertheless פעמים
שהכהן זורקן יותר משלושים אמה. pa’amim shekohein zorkan yoseir mishloshim amah.
There are times that a כהן kohein would have to throw it
more than thirty אמות. amos. How do you know that? Well let’s
talk about where is this place of the ashes that this that
the crop and the you know the feather have to be thrown
to, the feather. So it says ותנן, u’tnan, we taught in a
משנה mishnah in תמיד, Tamid, about how you would do the תרומת
הדשן, terumas hadashen, the removing of the ashes every morning. נטל מחתה
של כסף, natol machtah shel kesef, so the כהן kohein that got
the roll of the תרומת הדשן terumas hadashen would take a, you
know, a what’s it called like a shovel of silver, ועלה לראש
המזבח, ve’alah lerosh hamizbeach, he would go to the top of the
altar, ופינה את הגחלים אילך ואילך, upinas hagechalim ilech ve’ilech, and he
would sort of move the coals to each to both sides, וחתה
מן המאוכלות הפנימיות, vechata min hamauchalos hapnimiyos,
and he would scoop up ashes from the stuff that was deep
inside, you know, and had been totally burnt and consumed, וירד, veyarad,
and he would come down the ramp, הגיע לרצפה, hagia leritzpah, and
he would get to the ground, מחזיר פניו כלפי צפון, machazir panav
kelapei tzafon, he would turn his face to now he is facing
back towards the face of the altar, he’s he’s pointed north, והלך
למזרחו של כבש, veholach lemizrachah shel kevesh,
he would go to the east of the ramp as we saw
it said אצל המזבח קדמה, etzel hamizbeach kedma, so the place of
the ashes would be to the east of the ramp, כעשר
אמות, ke’eser amos, he’d go across ten אמות amos towards the מזבח,
mizbeach, so the ramp is thirty-two אמות, amot, he’d go ten אמות
amos in from the base of the ramp, you know, towards the
מזבח, mizbeach, twenty-two אמות amot away from the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, כעשר
אמות, ke’eser amos, צבר את הגחלים על גבי הרצפה, tzibeir es hagechalim
al gabei haritzpah,
he would pile up the, you know, the coals or the ashes
right there ten אמות amos in right by the side of the
ramp on the ground, רחוק מן הכבש שלושה טפחים, rachok min hakevesh
sheloshah tefachim, three טפחים tefachim removed from the from the ramp itself,
towards the east of the ramp. מקום שנותנים מוראה ונוצה ודישון מזבח
הפנימי, makom she’nosnim mor’ah venotzah vedishen mizbeach hapnimy, and the same place
would be where you would put the crop and the feather of
the bird of the עולה olah and also when you would clean
the inner מזבח mizbeach of the
קטורת, ktores, והמנורה, vehamenorah, and also when you would remove the ashes
from the מנורה. menorah. Okay, so that’s the משנה. mishnah. So what
does that show you? So it shows you that this place was
on the east side of the ramp, twenty-two אמות amot removed from
the base of the altar. So if the כהן kohein was standing
in the southeast corner, right, he would basically have to throw it
twenty-two אמות, amot, okay, you know, a little more because if this
is right next to the ramp, the ramp is sixteen אמות, amot,
the you know the מזבח mizbeach is thirty-two, so there’s eight אמות
amot on each side of the מזבח, mizbeach, but actually you have
to go in on each side, you know, one אמה amah for
the base and another אמה amah for the סובב soveiv for like
the middle thing that you go around, so it’s really like six
אמות amot till you get to the top corner of the מזבח.
mizbeach. All right, so if the כהן kohein was standing at the
southeast southeast corner, he’d have imagine a triangle, right, he’s going to
throw the diagonal, so the triangle has a one base is is
what do you call it is twenty-two, right, because he’s ten in,
so twenty-two from where that בית הדשן beis hadashen is till you
hit the... the wall of the מזבח Mizbeiach and then the other
base going to the corner is now another six. So 6 by
22 and that would be the diagonal. So that would be whatever
it would be, a little more than 22, we won't do the
math. Fine. So that would only be 22. How do you get
30? Ah, because what happens when he's not at the southeast corner,
but when he's at the southwest corner? So then think how far
he has to go. Okay, he has to go now the from
the east side of the ramp to the edge of the ramp
is 16, the ramp was 16 and from there to the corner
to the southwest corner is another six. That's 22. Now רשי Rashi
does exactly the math depending on where he was, was it 22,
was it 23, we won't worry about that. For simplicity we'll say
22. So now you've got a triangle that is defined by 22
in one direction to get from the ashes to the מזבח, Mizbeiach,
22 in another direction to get from that point in the מזבח
Mizbeiach to the other corner, to the southwest corner. And now you
have to do the diagonal. Okay.
So that diagonal, that's a classic Pythagorean theorem, 22, 22, so the
diagonal is 22 times the square root of 2. For the גמרא,
Gemara, the square root of 2 is 1.4, which is a pretty
good estimate. Okay, so 22 times 1.4,
you know, so 0.4 times 22 is 8.8, that's going to get
you 30.8.
All right, so that's what you're going to get, 30.8. So essentially
31.
So he says he'd have to throw 30 אמות, amot, this, you
know, 45 feet, this very light, you know, crop and whatever, the
gizzard, that really you have to have a lot of strength to
throw something that light that far. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
The גמרא Gemara says הני טפי מתלתין וחד הויין. Hanei Tfei Mi-Tlatim
ve-Chad Havian.
It wasn't just 30, it was even more than 31. I'm not
going to go exactly through the exact math how he got exactly
more than 31, but you can see that it's approximately 31. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, מקום גברא לא קשיב. Mekom Gavra
Lo Kashiv. He's not counting the place where the כהן Kohein himself
stood, you know, that's so, you know, so that's already where the
place he standing is itself one אמה, amah, so you subtract the
one אמה amah where he standing and it gets you closer to
30 אמות. amot. Okay, I think that's enough math for this.
Okay, כל העולים למזבח. Kol Ha-Olim La-Mizbeiach. So now it says anybody
would go up to the altar normally you would go counterclockwise because
what we taught actually the other day all the turnings you turn
are to the right and you'd go counterclockwise. But when you have
to do your business at the top of the מזבח, Mizbeiach, the
pouring of the wine or of the water or the עולת העוף
Olat Ha-Of if there are too many on the southeast corner and
you're doing that at the southwest corner, rather than doing the whole
rotation all around, you go straight to the southwest corner. You make
a left instead of a right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
מאי טעמא? Mai Taama? So why are you allowed to turn to
the left rather than the right? Why not just go the whole
way around? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan נסכים שמא יתעשנו. Nesachim
Shema Yitashnu.
Well the wine and the water is because they'll get smoky going
all the way around, they'll, you know, you have all of the
burning smoke of the מזבח Mizbeiach and that'll make them smoky and
then they will not be acceptable, they'll be פסול pasul if they
are, you know, if they get smoky. So that's why those you
would go the long way around. How about the bird? ועולת העוף
שמא תמות בעשן. Ve-Olat Ha-Of Shema Tamut Ba-Ashan. Similar concern, you know,
as you're going all the way around there's so much smoke it'll
kill this tiny little bird. So therefore you were able to take
a shortcut and go straight to the left.
רמיהו, Rami'ihu, I'll ask you on this that you say you could
go straight to the left. בא לו להקיף את המזבח. Ba Lo
Le-Hakif Et Ha-Mizbeiach. This is talking about a כהן גדול Kohein Gadol
and if the כהן גדול Kohein Gadol wants to bring the תמיד
Tamid rather than dividing it up amongst the many כהנים, Kohanim, the
כהן גדול Kohein Gadol could just go ahead and decide to do
the תמיד Tamid whenever he would want. Okay, and then it also
wouldn't be divided up, he would do all the parts of it.
So בא לו להקיף את המזבח, Ba Lo Le-Hakif Et Ha-Mizbeiach, so
he would then come to rotate around the altar after he had
gotten to the top and had offered up, you know, put all
of the various pieces of the meat on the dismembered pieces on
the actual fire. And now he has to rotate around it in
order to do the pouring of the wine. So בא לו להקיף
את המזבח, Ba Lo Le-Hakif Et Ha-Mizbeiach, מאין הוא מתחיל? Me-Ayin Hu
Matchil? Where does he begin? מקרן דרומית מזרחית. Mi-Keren Deromit Mizrachit. You
start from southeast. מזרחית צפונית, Mizrachit Tzonit, then northeast. צפונית מערבית, Tzonit
Maaravit, northwest. מערבית דרומית, Maaravit Deromit, and finally southwest. Okay, so the
normal counterclockwise rotation and then when he gets to the southwest, נותנים
לו יין לנסך, Notnim Lo Yayin Lenasech, and you give him the
wine to pour, you know, that's the נסכים Nesachim that go with
the עולה. Olah. So here you see he would go the long
way around, not the short way around. So there's an easy answer
here which is hinted to in the words נותנים לו יין לנסך.
Notnim Lo Yayin Lenasech. Not he would,
at that point he would be given the wine. So אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
top of סד עב, Samech Dalet Amud Bet,
says אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. הקפה ברגל. hakafa baregel.
So it's not exactly clear, I mean the words are clear, but
the primary point of the answer is not spelled out. No, he
would just walk around, but he wouldn't be transporting the wine. Okay,
if you're just going up just to do the pouring of the
wine, you take the wine with you and you make a left.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when he would do it, he would
be doing all parts, the meat and the wine. So he'd go
up, he'd burn the meat, he wasn't there just for the wine.
And then once he was there, he didn't have the wine with
him. He would go all the way around and then they would
give him the wine and so therefore there was not a concern
that the wine would get smoky. אמר רבא, amar Rava, דיקא נמי
דקתני, deika nami de-katni, that's also can be understood by a close
read of the text because it says נותנין לו יין לנסך, notnim
lo yayin lenasech, they would then give him the wine, ולא קתני
אומר לו נסך, ve-lo katni omer lo nasech, they wouldn't say pour
the wine, so it was clear that he didn't have the wine
with him until he got to that corner. שמע מינה, shema mina,
that is a good inference. It is a very good inference. Okay.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught, כל עולים למזבח עולים דרך
ימין ויורדים דרך שמאל. kol olim la-mizbe'ach olim derech yamin ve-yordim derech
smol.
So this is what we're taught, normally you up the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
you go up on the right-hand side, you know, all traffic to
the right, and then you come down on the left-hand side, meaning
it's always your right, you know, traffic is always on the right,
but if you're facing the מזבח, mizbe'ach, people go up on the
right and then they'll come down on your left. עולים דרך מזרח,
olim derech mizrach,
it's another way of saying it, they go up on the east
side, ויורדים דרך מערב, ve-yordim derech ma'arav, and then come down on
the west side of the ramp. חוץ מן העולה לשלושה דברים אלו,
chutz min ha-oleh le-shlosha devarim elu,
except for if you're going up for these three things, שעולים דרך
מערב ויורדים דרך מערב. she-olim derech ma'arav ve-yordim derech ma'arav. You go
up on the west and come down on the west. So if
you're doing the wine or the water or the עולת העוף, olat
ha-of, which is being done at the southwest, you're going up on
the west and come down on the west. Now I should say
this is a little spells out something that wasn't clear in the
משנה. Mishnah. In the משנה Mishnah I would have assumed, no, traffic
stays on the right, you know, the normal side of the road
as much as possible. You go up on the east side, once
you get to the top you make a left. You know, then
people don't have to worry about running against, you know, the normal
flow of traffic except like when you're at the very top. And
actually you're pretty safe there because normally nobody is traversing from the
east side of the ramp to the west side of the ramp.
If you're going up in the east and then it's going counter-clockwise
and coming down on the west, nobody is traversing that space between
the east and the west side of the ramp. So if you
go up in the east and then you make a left, there's
very little traffic to run against. This ברייתא baraita is actually quite
surprising, that says you would go up on the left because then
you'd have to fight against all the traffic coming down. I really
don't understand that so well, but that's what it
says. עולים דרך מערב ויורדים דרך מערב. olim derech ma'arav ve-yordim derech
ma'arav. עולים דרך ימין ויורדים דרך ימין. olim derech yamin ve-yordim derech
yamin. Now that's bizarre, it should have said left. Until now we've
been referring to the west as the left when you're facing the
altar. So the גמרא Gemara asks that. דרך ימין? derech yamin? What
do you mean on the right? דרך שמאל הוא. derech smol hu.
You're coming down on the west, okay, when you're doing these three
things you go up on the left and come down on the
left. אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, said Ravina, תני שמאל, tani smol, fine,
it was a mistake, it should say left. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
Rava says, מאי ימין ימין דמזבח. mai yamin yamin de-mizbe'ach. No, when
it says the right, it means, you know, it's always like when
you're talking to somebody and you're facing them, are you talking about
that person's right or your right? You know, it's the reverse. So
here when it says you come down on the right, it means,
you know, if you imagine the מזבח mizbe'ach as a person, the
face of it, right, is where the ramp is, right, so then,
you know, so when when you're coming down on the west side,
you're coming down on the person's right. It's your left if you're
facing it, but it's the מזבח's mizbe'ach right. Okay. So he says,
ומאי שמאל שמאל דגברא. u-mai smol smol de-gavra. When it said the
first part of the ברייתא baraita said, you know, that people come
down on the left, they mean the left when you're facing the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. But when it said you come down on the right,
also speaking to the west, it means the right of the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Which is very confusing and the גמרא Gemara says, וניתני או
אידי ואידי דמזבח או אידי ואידי דגברא קשיא. ve-nisni o aidei ve-aidei
de-mizbe'ach o aidei ve-aidei de-gavra kashya. Be consistent! Either constantly refer to
the point of view of the altar or constantly refer to the
point of view of the person facing the altar. So it is
very strange that it initially referred to the west as the left
from the perspective of the person facing and then in the end
it referred to the west as the right from the perspective of
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, which is why here it's just it is a
lot easier to just amend the text. Okay. Anyway, that is the
three things that were done on the southwest corner.
Next משנה. Mishnah. Now we're going to that we're talking about the
bird sacrifices, we spoke about the חטאת chatat that was done at
the base and so on and now we're going to speak more
about the חטאת chatat and also then move to the עולה. olah.
חטאת
העוף כיצד היתה נעשית?
chatat ha-of keitzad
hayeta na'asit? How would the חטאת העוף chatat ha-of be done?
היה מולק את ראשה ממול עורף, haya molek et roshah mi-mul oref,
you would sever the head from like the nape of the
neck, ואינו מבדיל, ve-eino mavdil, but
you would not sever it, I should say you would not sever
it. You would like slice it and it was done with like
the thumbnail of the כהן, Kohen, but it would not sever. Now,
not sever means two things: it means that it would not physically
cut the head off of the whole bird, and also it means
it would only cut one of the סימנים, simanim, either the trachea
or the esophagus but not both. ומזה מדמה על קיר המזבח, Umazeh
midamah al kir hamizbeach, and the blood would squirt out to the
wall of the מזבח, Mizbeach, and this would actually be as we've
learned, this would be the southwest
corner. שיירי הדם, Sheyarei hadam, and then the remainder of the blood
היה מתמצה אל היסוד, haya mitmatzeh el hayesod, would sort of dribble
down to the base. Now מתמצה mitmatzeh refers to two things: it
means that it would go naturally, it would just dribble down the
stuff that had hit the wall, hit the corner of the מזבח,
Mizbeach, but
also ימצה yimatzeh is also understood to mean that if there's anything
left in the bird, you squeeze it out, you push it against
the wall of the מזבח Mizbeach and the remainder comes down, and
that's similar to spilling out the שיירי הדם sheyarei hadam of the
חטאת. Chattas. מתמצה ליסוד. Mitmatzeh liyesod. ואין המזבח אלא דמה, Ve'ein hamizbeach
ela damah, the altar would only get the blood, there would be
nothing burnt from it. In all other mammal sacrifices something would be
burnt, at least the fats and so on, but here only the
blood. והכול לכהנים, Vehakol lakohanim, and the entire bird itself, the meat
would be eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught: והזה מדם החטאת, Vehizah midam hachattas, you shall spray from the
blood of the חטאת, Chattas, referring to the bird. מגוף החטאת, Miguf
hachattas,
it says from the חטאת. Hachattas. It's not that you collect it
in a vessel and you throw it from the vessel. The blood
squirts straight from the bird straight onto the altar. מגוף החטאת. Miguf
hachattas. הכיצד? Hakeitzad? How do you do this? אוחז בראשה ובגופה, Ochez
beroshah uvegufah,
you hold the head and the body, because since you haven't severed
the head, you want to sort of bend it away so that
the blood can squirt straight out. So you're sort of holding the
head down, letting it squirt out. אוחז בראשה ובגופה, Ochez beroshah uvegufah,
ומזה על קיר המזבח, umazeh al kir hamizbeach,
and it hits the wall of the altar. And now just to
be clear, ולא על קיר הכבש, velo al kir hakevesh, it doesn't
hit, not the ramp, ולא על קיר היכל, velo al kir heichal,
and not hitting the wall of the
היכל. Heichal. It says על המזבח, al hamizbeach, but okay, ולא על
קיר אולם, velo al kir ulam, and not on the wall of
the אולם, Ulam, על קיר המזבח. al kir hamizbeach. ואיזה זה קיר
התחתון? Ve'eizeh zeh kir hatachton? It is the lower wall. It is
not the part above, above the middle line, the חוט הסיקרא, Chut
hasikra, it is below the middle line. או אינו אלא קיר העליון?
O eino ela kir ha'elyon? How do you know this? How do
you know a חטאת, Chattas, the blood of a bird, it goes
below?
ודין הוא, Vadin hu, and I could make an argument why it
should go above. ומה בהמה שלא עולה למטה
חטאתה למעלה? Umah behemah shelo olah lematah chattasah lemalah? By a בהמה,
behemah, a mammal, cow, sheep, we know that
the עולה olah is below the line and the חטאת chattas is
at the corners above the line. עוף שעולתו למעלה, Of she'olaso lemalah,
and off that the עולה, olah, which we'll see in the next
משנה, Mishna, the עולה olah goes at the top. אינו דין שחטאתו
למעלה? Eino din shechattaso lemalah? Certainly the חטאת, chattas, which by a
בהמה behemah is למעלה, lemalah, if by the birds even the עולה
olah is on the top, certainly the חטאת chattas should be on
the top. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, והנשאר בדם ימצה אל יסוד המזבח,
vehanish'ar badam yimatzeh el yesod hamizbeach,
what is the remaining of the blood shall be squeezed out and
dribbled out to the base of the altar. So how does this
show you that it's below the line? קיר ששיריו מתמצין ליסוד. Kir
sheshirav mitmatzin liyesod. It has to be on the wall that when
the blood dribbles down from where it hit the wall, it will
hit the base. If you go above the line, now there is
an אמה amah between the middle line until you get to the
סובב, sovev, the walk-around. But there are places above the line, most
of the places above the line, if the blood were to hit
there, it would hit the
walk-around, it would, because the walk-around, it would be a protrusion, so
it would not go straight to the base. You have to get
only if you're below the line can you be certain that the
blood will come straight to the base, and that shows you that
it is squirted below the line. ואיזה זה
קיר התחתון, Ve'eizeh zeh kir hatachton, that is the bottom part of
the wall. ונעביד מעילאי והדר נעביד מתתאי? Vena'avid me'ilai vehadar na'avid mittatai?
One minute, but there's two things: there's the squirting of the blood
and then there's the squeezing out. So why not say the squirting
is above the line, that's the עיקר ikar getting of the blood
on the מזבח, mizbeach, and then when you squeeze it out and
it goes straight to the base, the squeezing out comes the like
the spilling of the שיירים, shirayim, that is below the
line? והדר נעביד מתתאי? Vahadar nevad mitatai?
So why not do the first half above and the second part
below? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so Rava says, מי כתיב ימצה? mi
ksiv yimatzeh? It doesn't say the blood you shall squeeze out. ימצה
כתיב, Yimatzeh ksiv, it says shall be squeezed out, or it can
also mean like shall dribble down. So even
though the פסוק pasuk is read that there are two things by
חז"ל, Chazal, there's the squirting and then the pressing of the remainder
like the spilling of the שיירים, shirayim, what the גמרא Gemara here
is... acknowledging is that it could be read as the remainder of
the blood will naturally dribble down to the base of the מזבח,
mizbeach, not that you do a separate act. And that, so if
it's going to naturally dribble down from the blood that already hit
the altar, it means it has to hit the altar below the
line where it will go straight to the base, because above the
line it could hit the walk-around. Okay, דממילא
משמע, de-memaila mashma, it'll naturally go to the base. אמר רב זוטרא
בר טוביא אמר רב, Amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvya amar Rav, כיצד
מולקין חטאת העוף? Keitzad molkin chatas ha-of? How do you do the
מליקה? melikah? How do you hold the bird and then use your
thumb to cut the neck? Okay, אוחז גפיו בשתי אצבעותיו, ochez gappav
bi-shtei etzbe'otav, so it assumes that you're going to put the basic
bird in the palm of your hand. Then you hold the wings
with two of your fingers; רש"י Rashi says it's basically your index
finger and your pointer finger.
ושתי רגליו בשתי אצבעותיו, u-shtei raglav bi-shtei etzbe'otav, and its feet are
held in your other two fingers, your pinky and your index finger.
ומותח צוארה על רוחב גודלו, u-moteyach tzavara al rochev gudalov, you stretch
out the neck on the width of your thumb, basically the curve
between your index finger and your thumb, that's sort of where the
neck is hanging on, and this is your right
hand because everything is in the right hand. על רוחב גודלו, al
rochev gudalov, ומולק, u-molak, and then you use your thumb and the
fingernail of your thumb with the neck stretched out there between your
thumb and your index finger, you use your fingernail to slice the
neck. Okay, not exactly, it feels very hard in terms of the
angle to do that, which is why the גמרא Gemara is about
to say that this was very difficult. במתניתא תנא, be-masnisa tana, in
a ברייתא Baraisa we taught, ציפרא מלברא, tzipra mi-le-bara, not that you
would hold the bird in the palm of your hand, but the
actual body of the bird would be at the back of your
hand. But same basic idea: אוחז גפיו בשתי אצבעותיו, ochez gappav bi-shtei
etzbe'otav, the wings in two fingers, ושתי רגליו בשתי אצבעותיו, u-shtei raglav
bi-shtei etzbe'otav, the feet in two fingers, ומותח צוארה על רוחב שתי
אצבעותיו. u-moteyach tzavara al rochev shtei etzbe'otav. So if the bird is
sort of at the back of your hand, the neck is sort
of not so much in the nick in between your thumb and
the forefinger, it's more stretched out behind your fingers.
ומולק, u-molak, and then you would do the מליקה. melikah. וזו היא
עבודה קשה שבמקדש, ve-zo hi avodah kashah she-be-mikdash, this was the most
difficult עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to be able
to do this. And you could imagine, right, to be able to
use your thumb to slaughter the neck of a bird but also
holding it this way, the angle isn't good. So then the גמרא
Gemara just says, זו היא ותו לא? zu hi ve-su lo? What,
this is the hardest עבודה? avodah? There's nothing else that's as difficult?
ואיכא קמיצה וחפינה, ve-ika kemitzah ve-chafinah, we teach in other places that
learning how to do the קמיצה kemitzah to take exactly a hand
breadth and smooth it out with your thumb and pinky—I don't exactly
get why that is so super difficult—but also the חפינה, chafinah, the
shoveling of the coals that they would do for the קטורת ketores
in the for the burning of the קטורת ketores on יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. Okay, so we taught that those were also of the
hardest עבודות avodos in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אלא אימא, ela
eima, זו עבודה קשה מעבודות קשות שבמקדש, zu avodah kashah me-avodos kashos
she-ba-mikdash, it is not the most difficult, it is among the most
difficult עבודות avodos in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, very good,
that was the חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. Next משנה, Mishnah, and the
very long משנה, Mishnah, we're not going to finish this משנה Mishnah
today, we'll get to the משנה Mishnah at the end of the
דף, daf, tomorrow we'll finish the משנה Mishnah and see the גמרא.
Gemara. עולת העוף כיצד נעשה? olas ha-of keitzad na'asah? Now how do
you do the עולת העוף, olas ha-of, which was again at the
top of the מזבח? mizbeach? So עלה לכבש, alah la-kevesh, you'd go
up the ramp, ופנה לסובב, u-fanah la-sovev, and here you'd get off
in the middle of the ramp and you'd go to the walk-around.
Okay, so the walk-around went from the west side of the ramp—excuse
me, the east side of the ramp—there was a sub-ramp as we
talked that would get you to the walk-around. By the way, רש"י
Rashi points out that when you would do it at the there
was too many עולת העוף olas ha-of at the corner and you
would do it at the southwest
corner, there, remember it says you made an immediate left. So there
you would actually go all the way to the top of the
מזבח mizbeach and make an immediate left. Okay,
but because there's no sub side ramp to get you to that
left corner directly. But here when you're going up and you're going
to the east, you take the side ramp and that gets you
to the walk-around that starts at the southeast corner and that's where
you do
the
עולת העוף. olas ha-of. היה מולק את ראשה ממול ערפה, hayah molek
es roshah mi-mul orephah, you would slice the head from the nape
of the neck.
ומבדיל, u-mavdil, and you would completely sever. You would cut both the
trachea and the esophagus and also you would sever the head from
the body. ומיצה את דמה על קיר המזבח, u-mitze es damah al
kir ha-mizbeach, as opposed to the חטאת chatas where first it would
squirt out and then the remainder you would squeeze by pressing pressing
it against the wall. Here, it would directly start by being pressed
against the wall, there would be no squirting out. Not exactly sure
why they, I mean, whatever, it's based on פסוקים, psukim, but I
can't exactly explain the logic. Okay, על המזבח, al hamizbeach, so there
would only be one thing, not two things. נטל את הראש, natal
es harosh, and here it's an עולה, olah, so you're going to
burn it, so you take the head, which is now a separate
unit, והקיף בית מליקתו למזבח, v'hikif beis melikaso l'mizbeach, okay, and you
push the place of where it had been cut, where it had
been severed against the מזבח. mizbeach. That would be the squeezing out
of the blood against the מזבח, mizbeach, okay. I mean, it already
said ומיצה את דמו על קיר המזבח, umitzah es damo al kir
hamizbeach, but now it's getting a little bit more specific. Maybe fundamentally
the first מיצת דמו mitzas damo is the מיצת דמו, mitzas damo,
the squeezing out from the body of the bird. Now you're going
to squeeze out the remainder of the blood from the head of
the bird, okay. So you take the head of the bird, you
push up the place where it was severed, the cut against the
מזבח, mizbeach, and you squeeze out the remainder of the blood from
the head of the bird,
ובמזבח וספקו במלח, ub'mizbeach v'safko b'melach, and then you sort of like
put it in salt, you absorb it in salt because everything that
you put on the מזבח mizbeach has salt on it, וזרקה על
גבי האישים v'zarka al gabbei ha'ishim and you cast it on the
fire. בא לו לגוף, ba lo l'guf, now you come to the
body and again presumably you've already squeezed out the blood from the
body, והסיר את המוראה ואת הנוצה, v'hisir es hamursah v'es hanutzah, and
you remove the crop and the feather that's like on the outside
of the skin opposite the crop, ואת בני מעיים v'es bnei me'ayin
and the innards היוצאים עמם hayotzim imam that come out
when you remove these things, והשליכן לבית הדשן v'hishlichan l'veis hadeshen and
you throw them 22 אמות amot as we discussed before to where
the ashes are placed on the east side of the ramp, and
that's what you would do. לא הסיר את המוראה ולא את הנוצה
ואת בני מעיים היוצאים עמם, lo hisir es hamursah v'lo es hanutzah
v'es bnei me'ayin hayotzim imam, if you did not take out the
crop and these innards, ולא ספקו במלח, v'lo safko b'melach, and if
you did not put the salt on it, כל ששינה בה לאחר
מיצת הדם כשרה, kol sheshina ba l'acharei mitzas hadam kshera, even though
you've done the wrong thing, like exactly like the animal sacrifices,
it's כשר kosher once the עבודה avoda of the דם dam is
done. So it says
as long as, all of this as long as you did the
squeezing out of the blood correctly, even though this thing about removing
the innards, how you're putting the salt on, how you're burning it
on the מזבח, mizbeach, even if you've done it incorrectly, the קרבן
korban is still כשר, kosher, okay. כל ששינה
לאחר מיצת הדם כשרה.
kol sheshina
l'acharei mitzas hadam kshera. Now if you did something wrong though with
the דם עבודה, dam avoda, then it's going to become invalid. הבדיל
בחטאת ולא הבדיל בעולה פסול. hivdil b'chatas v'lo hivdil b'olah pasul. Let's
say with the חטאת chatas you actually did more than you were
supposed to, you severed it, either you completely removed the head or
even if you just cut both the trachea and the esophagus, or
you did not sever by the עולה, olah, then it's invalid. That's
still when you're dealing with the דם. dam. מיצת את דם הראש
ולא מיצת דם הגוף פסולה. mitzas es dam harosh v'lo mitza dam
haguf psula. Now,
if you squeeze out the blood from the head but not from
the body, it's invalid. The key blood is that of the body.
דם הגוף ולא מיצת דם הראש כשרה. dam haguf v'lo mitza dam
harosh kshera. If you squeeze out the blood from the body but
not from the head, right, the first in the משנה mishna when
it spoke about the fundamental squeezing of the blood,
it
spoke, it was talking about the body, מיצת הדם, mitzas hadam, then
it's going to still be כשר. kosher. ולא מיצת דם הראש
כשרה. v'lo mitza dam harosh kshera. חטאת העוף שמלכה, chatas ha'of shemalka,
now we're just going to talk about the normal stuff we've been
talking about from the beginning of the מסכת masechet about לשמה lishma
and שלא לשמה shelo lishma and פיגול. pigul. So let's take a
look. חטאת העוף שמלכה שלא לשמה, chatas ha'of shemalka shelo lishma, if
you did the מליקה שלא לשמה melika shelo lishma which corresponds to
the שחיטה shchita by an animal sacrifice, או מיצה דמה שלא לשמה
o mitzah damah shelo lishma or you squeezed out the blood which
is sort of like the זריקה zrika of the דם dam or
the putting of the דם dam I should say on the corners
about a חטאת, chatas, okay,
so as we know by a חטאת chatas when it's שלא לשמה
shelo lishma it's invalid. If it's לשמה ושלא לשמה lishma v'shelo lishma
or you had both intentions, one of the עבודות avodos was לשמה,
lishma, one was שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, או שלא לשמה ולשמה פסול.
o shelo lishma v'lishma pasul. Anyway, if you do one of these
key עבודות שלא לשמה, avodos shelo lishma, it's invalid just like by
a חטאת chatas of a בהמה. behema. Except here there are really
only two עבודות, avodos, there's only the מליקה melika and the squeezing
out of the blood. There are not four עבודות. avodos. עולת העוף
כשרה, olos ha'of kshera, but by the bird עולה, olah, it's כשר
kosher because שלא לשמה shelo lishma by an עולה olah is כשר,
kosher, ובלבד שלא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה ubilvad shelo ala l'baalim l'shem
chova but the owners did not fulfill their obligation. אחד חטאת העוף
ואחד עולת העוף שמלכן ושמיצה דמן, echad chatas ha'of v'echad olos ha'of
shemalkan v'shemitza daman, now, whether a חטאת chatas or an עולה, olah,
now we're moving from שלא לשמה shelo lishma to פיגול. pigul. If
you did either the מליקה melika or the squeezing of the blood,
the two key עבודות, avodos, if you did them דבר שדרכו davar
shedarko
to eat the thing that's normally eaten, meaning to eat the meat
of the חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, ולהקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר, u-le-haktir davar
she-darko le-haktir,
or to burn with the intent or to eat the meat or
to burn the thing you would normally burn, the meat of the
עולת העוף, olas ha-of, ולהקטיר חוץ למקומו פסול ואין בו כרת, u-le-haktir
chutz li-mkomo pasul ve-ein bo kares,
if you had the intent to do it in the wrong place,
to go ahead and eat it outside of the עזרה, azarah, the
קרבן korban would be invalid but there would not be כרת. kares.
חוץ לזמנו, chutz li-zmano, if you had the intent to do it
at the wrong time, פיגול וחייב עליו כרת, pigul ve-chayav alav kares,
you would make it פיגול pigul and if you were to eat
it you would get כרת. kares. ובלבד שיקריב המתיר כמצוותו, u-vilvad she-yakriv
ha-matir ke-mitzvaso, but only, it only becomes פיגול pigul if you do
the remaining of the thing that makes it a כשר kosher קרבן
korban in the correct way, or in the פיגול pigul way but
not in a way that invalidates it from a different perspective. כיצד
קרב המתיר כמצוותו, keitzad karav ha-matir ke-mitzvaso, what is, how is this?
מלק בשתיקה, malak bi-shtikah, if you did the מליקה melikah without any
intent, ומיצה דם חוץ לזמנו, u-mitzas dam chutz li-zmano,
and you did the squeezing with a פיגול pigul intent, או שמלק
חוץ לזמנו ומיצה דם בשתיקה, o she-malak chutz li-zmano u-mitzas dam bi-shtikah,
or the מליקה melikah was פיגול pigul and the מיצוי mitzuy was
with no intent, או שמלק ומיצה דם חוץ לזמנו, o she-malak u-mitzas
dam chutz li-zmano, or both of the עבודות avodos were with a
פיגול pigul intent, זהו שקרב המתיר כמצוותו. zehu she-karav ha-matir ke-mitzvaso.
Then it's like everything was done either with פיגול pigul or with
nothing and then it becomes פיגול. pigul. Okay, however, כיצד לא קרב
המתיר כמצוותו, keitzad lo karav ha-matir ke-mitzvaso,
what is not doing it properly? מלק חוץ למקומו מיצה דם חוץ
לזמנו, malak chutz li-mkomo mitzas dam chutz li-zmano, if one of the
עבודות avodos was a חוץ למקומו, chutz li-mkomo, either the מליקה melikah
was חוץ למקומו chutz li-mkomo and the squeezing was חוץ לזמנו, chutz
li-zmano, או שמלק חוץ לזמנו ומיצה דם חוץ למקומו, o she-malak chutz
li-zmano u-mitzas dam chutz li-mkomo, or the מליקה melikah was חוץ לזמנו
chutz li-zmano and the squeezing was חוץ למקומו, chutz li-mkomo, so anyway
there was something else invalidating it other than פיגול, pigul, the חוץ
למקומו, chutz li-mkomo, או שמלק ומיצה דם חוץ למקומו, o she-malak u-mitzas
dam chutz li-mkomo, or if you did both of them חוץ למקומו,
chutz li-mkomo, all of that would be a case of לא קרב
המתיר כמצוותו lo karav ha-matir ke-mitzvaso and it would not become פיגול.
pigul. We will end here and we will continue with this משנה
mishnah top of ס"ה samech hey tomorrow.